<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>By the King, orders for thorow-posts, and curriers, riding in post in our affaires</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1603-1625 : James I)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1621</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 3 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A69350</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 8675.2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S386</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">22343775</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 22343775</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1067</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A69350)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1067)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1752:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>By the King, orders for thorow-posts, and curriers, riding in post in our affaires</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1603-1625 : James I)</author>
                  <author>James I, King of England, 1566-1625.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 broadside.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Bonham Norton and Iohn Bill ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1621.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reprints STC 8346.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Postal service --  England.</term>
               <term>Proclamations --  Great Britain.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  James I, 1603-1625.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1603-1625.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:1067:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 4 -->
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> By the King.</head>
            <head type="sub">¶ Orders for thorow-Poſts, and Curriers, riding in Poſt in Our Affaires.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He lords of the Priuie Councell endeauoring heretofore the like furtherance of the Seruice of the State,</hi> aſwell in horſing ſuch as ride on their Princes Affaires, as the ſpeedie diſpatch of Packets in all places, where Poſtes were erected and ordeined, conſidering, that for the ſeruice of the one, a daily Fee is allowed, and for the other no certaine wages at all, but the hire of the Horſes let out, and that often ill payed, whereby they ſtand not ſo bound to the one, as to attend the other: And that the Townes and Countreys beſides became many wayes vexed and perplexed, by the ouer great liberty of riders in Poſte, eſpecially by ſuch as pretend publike Seruice by ſpeciall Commiſſion, contrary to the Kings meaning, or their Lordſhips Orders: Who minding no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more, then the particular good of his Seruants and ſubjects; for the benefite of the one, reliefe of the other, and more regard to the good vſage of all Owners of Horſes, and the beaſtes themſelues, did thinke it expedient, to digeſt and ſet downe ſundry neceſſary Orders indifferent for all parties to obſerue and follow, Which Orders being by vs reuiewed and conſidered, are now according to the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of the times, thought meete to bee eſtſoones allowed and publiſhed. The execution whereof, we ſeriouſly recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending to the Maſter and Comptroller of all Our Poſtes, for the better warranting and directing of Poſtes, ſo farre as this Seruice may concerne them, Wee doe hereby ſtraitly charge and command, all and euery Lieutenants of Shires, deputy Lieutenants, Iuſtices of al Aſſiſes and Peace, Sheriffes, Mayors, Bailiffes, Conſtables, Headboroughs, and all other his Officers, Miniſters, &amp; louing ſubjects, to be aiding and aſſiſting to the ſame, with their vtmoſt helpe, authority and countenance where need ſhall require, as they tender the furtherance of the ſeruice of the State, and our diſpleaſure.</p>
            <p n="1">1. FIrſt it is ordered, That in all places where Poſtes are laid for the Packet, they alſo as perſons moſt fit, ſhall haue the benefit and preheminence of letting, furniſhing &amp; appointing of Horſes to all riding in Poſte, (that is to ſay) with Horne and guide by Commiſſion or other wiſe, And to that end ſhall keepe, and entertaine of their owne, or haue in a readineſſe vnder their direction, ſuch and ſo many able and ſufficient Poſt-horſes, with conuenient furniture, as their owne abilities will beare, or that the contributorie prouiſion of the Townes and Countreys ſhall enable them vnto, or afford. And if it fall out that Curriers or Thorow-Poſts, riding in our Affaires by ſpeciall Commiſſion, come ſo thicke, or in ſuch numbers, that their ordinary prouiſion will not ſuffice, then the Conſtables of the places where they dwell, with the aſſiſtance of the chiefe Magiſtrates there, and of the countreys adioyning, (being required in our name) ſhal take vy, bring in, and ſupply the Poſtes with horſes where they may be had or hired.</p>
            <p n="2">2 ANd like as in the Orders for the carying of the Packets, the furtherance of our ſeruice and the State is only ay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med at, ſo in this it is intended, that none be holden to ride on publike affaires, but with ſpeciall Commiſſion, &amp; the ſame ſigned either by one of our principall Secretaries of State, or ſixe at the leaſt of our Priuy Councell, or the Maſter and Comptroller generall of the Poſtes, for all iourneys outwards, and from the Court onely. And to the Court, the Lords of the Priuy Councell of Scotland, any Lieutenant, Deputy of Gouernors in Ireland, the Preſidents of Councels, or Vicepreſidents eſtabliſhed in the North, or in the Marches of Walles, the Gouernor of Barwiche, Any Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour, Gouernours of Townes, or Agents beyond the Seas, The Warden of the Cinque Ports, or his Lieutenant of Douer, ſpecially ſending to the Court, to the body of the Councell, or Secretaries of State, or any Pachet ſo directed, that it may appeare, the party diſpatched there with, rideth in our ſpecial Affaires, (the Ambaſſadors of forreine Princes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in this our Realme, and the ordinary Poſts for France and Flanders allowed, and by their badges ſufficiently commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated, excepted) and of all ſuch ſo riding in publique Affaires, it ſhall be lawfull for the Poſtes, or the owners of the Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to demand for the hire of each Horſe after the rate of two pence halfepeny the mile, (beſides the Guides groats.) But of all others riding Poſte with Horne and Guide, about their priuate buſineſſes, the hire and prices are leſt to the parties diſcretions to agree and compound within themſelues.</p>
            <p n="3">3. IT ſhall not be lawful for any perſon whatſoeuer riding in Poſt by Commiſſion or other wiſe, to take and ride away the Horſe or Horſes of any man, Poſte or other, not hauing firſt or aforehand fully payd and ſatiſfied for the price and hire vnto the Owners or the Poſt for them, nor ride them further then the next immediate Stage without changing, without the knowledge and conſent of the Poſte of the Stage, by whom he rideth in Poſte, nor charge any Horſe ſo taken to ride in Poſt with any Male, or burden, (beſides his Rider) that exceedeth the weight of thirty pounds: Neither ſhall any man ſo riding in Poſt, offer to ride any mans Horſe aboue ſeuen miles the houre in Summer, <hi>viz.</hi> From the firſt of Aprill, till the laſt of September; nor aboue ſixe in Winter, which ſhall be accounted the reſt of the yeere: And if any ſhall wilfully diſobey herein, or in any point hereof to the manifeſt hurt or hinderance of the Horſe his Owner, The Officers and Magiſtrates of the place vpon complaint made, ſhall ſtay the parties offending vntill they haue giuen preſent ſatiſfaction, or ſufficient ſecuritie to repay the damage.</p>
            <p n="4">FInally, as it is onely intended that our ſeruice in this kind, be at all hands furthered, and the Poſts to that end, in all their wants and wrongs to right themſelues by the help and authority of the Magiſtrates, Townes &amp; Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys as aboueſaid: So if the ſeruice ſhall ſeeme vnto any Poſt a burden ouergreat for his priuate ſtate to beare and vndertake, and the Townes and Countreys (notwithſtanding the eaſe and quiet they reape thereby) no way wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to countenance, encourage or enable him thereto: or otherwiſe in regard of yeres or indiſpoſition, ſhal not ſee reaſon to vnderlie the charge and trouble of the ſeruice, as being a hinderance to his ſpeciall duety in the ſeruice of the Packet: The Poſte in ſuch caſe attending his peculiar charge, the Conſtables and Magiſtrates of the places ſhall take order from time to time, that Horſes be prouided for all riding in Poſte by Commiſſion, or specially ſent in our Affaires as beforeſaid, in ſuch fort as they were ſubject to do before there were any Poſts there, and as in places where are yet no ſtanding Poſts at all. Vnto whom alſo our pleaſure is, that theſe Orders ſhall be in force, and auaileable (being deliuered them from the Maſter and Comptroller of the Poſts) ſo farre as they, and any branch of them may concerne the furtherance of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like ſeruice, or their owne reliefe.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Signed by his Maieſtie, and ſubſcribed by 
<list>
                     <item>Charles Stanhop Knight of the Bath,</item>
                     <item>Lord Stanhop of Harington, Maſter and Comptroller generall of his Highneſſe Poſtes.</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
               <lb/>
God ſaue the King.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Imprinted at London by Bonham Norton and Iohn Bill, Printers to the Kings moſt Excellent Maieſtie. ANNO 1621.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
